[music]
>> History is often presented as a set of
facts [music] and dates.
The victories and defeats
of monarchs and presidents
all consigned to an unchanging past.
>> Good morning.
>> Good morning to you as well, Lucy.
>> But it's not like that at all. History
is the knitting [music] together of
rival interpretations,
deliberate manipulations of the truth,
and sometimes
alternative facts.
In this series, I'll be lifting the lid
on three of American history's greatest
national stories.
The Revolutionary War of Independence.
Is the story of the Founding Fathers
built on fibs?
United States supremacy in the Cold War.
American dream or nuclear nightmare?
And [music] in this program, the
American Civil War.
It's gone down in history as a battle to
liberate the slaves [music] in the South
and to reunite the nation.
But is that really true? [music]
>> We like to think of Lincoln as someone
who starts the war [music] to free
African Americans, and the reality is
quite different.
>> The story of this bloody conflict has
been told and retold, shaping the
culture and politics of the nation with
epic tales like Gone with the Wind.
>> I'm getting Scarlett O'Hara's waist as
we speak.
>> And it's still on.
Conflicting accounts of the Civil War
continue to divide the nation to this
day.
But history is a murky business.
And the story of the Civil War is
stuffed full of some of American
history's biggest [music] fibs.
The American Civil War broke out in
April 1861.
By the time it ended four years later,
over 600,000 Americans had been killed.
That's more than in [music] World War I
and World War II combined.
The northern Union forces had defeated
southern Confederates.
President Abraham Lincoln was the heroic
victor.
And this is his memorial.
I'd say that there's something extra
monumental about this monument. It's got
utter self-confidence, hasn't it?
And every stone within it tells a story.
There are 36 of those columns, which
represent the 36 states that ended up
being in the Union after the war. And
you can read all their names, too, round
the top. Arkansas, Michigan, Florida,
they're all there. It's a real symbol of
togetherness.
Lincoln has saved the Union and ended
the divisions of the Civil War.
The great unifier himself is made of 175
tons of southern marble from the state
of Georgia.
Stone from the north and the south is
combined throughout this temple.
It's an image of the union in masonry.
And presidents ever since have
celebrated Lincoln's achievement.
>> That's what Abraham Lincoln understood.
He had his skeptics, he had his
setbacks, but through his will and his
words, he moved a nation and helped free
a people.
>> With the exception of the late great
Abraham Lincoln, I can be more
presidential than any president that's
ever held this office. That I can tell
you.
>> [cheering]
>> The memorial is telling a powerful
version of the story, the official
version, if you like. But history is
made up of facts and interpretations and
distortions and sometimes downright
lies.
And the story of the American Civil War
is one of the most contested stories of
all. So, I'm left wondering, could the
Lincoln Memorial itself be telling one
of American history's biggest fibs?
>> [music]
>> To find out how the history of the Civil
War has been shaped and manipulated, I'm
heading south to Georgia.
And I'll be asking if Abraham Lincoln
really was a saintly emancipator
dedicated to ending slavery and whether
his victory in the Civil War really did
reunite the nation.
It all started in the mansions of
wealthy slave owners whose way of life
was under threat.
>> Slavery is the thing that the entire
American economy at this point really
rests. The number of slaves in the south
will grow from approximately about
800,000 in 1790 up to 4 million by the
time of the Civil War. Slaves themselves
were were worth more than they had ever
been. A prime field hand male was worth
somewhere between a thousand and fifteen
hundred dollars. So, if you do the math
by today's numbers, it's anywhere
between two and nine trillion dollars.
Slaves and slavery was worth more than
all of the factories,
all of the warehouses, all of the
railroads, all they all the everything
else in the economy of America.
Slaves dwarfed that.
>> Today the USA has 50 states, but in 1861
there were only 34.
The Civil War began as a clash [music]
between the 19 northern states which had
abolished slavery
and 11 southern states whose economy
[music] was built on slave labor.
At the same time, huge areas of the
American West [music] were just
beginning to emerge as new states.
Would they adopt the economic model of
the north
or the south?
>> Well, the issue in the western
territories is whether or not slavery is
going to be allowed to exist in the
west.
And the question then for the United
States is, as this territory which is
unorganized now becomes states, will we
allow those states to be free or will we
allow them to be slave? The issue is not
so much about slavery where it exists,
but slavery where people want it to
exist or not to exist depending on their
perspective. And there are people who
can see that this is going to be the
powder keg that's going to set this
whole
>> [music]
>> sectional conflict off.
>> So, the war didn't start out as Abraham
Lincoln's crusade to liberate enslaved
people at all.
It was all about money.
Northerners feared they'd be unable to
compete if slavery was allowed to take
root in the new Western states.
And Southerners worried that slave
labor, the bedrock of their economy,
might be abolished altogether if it was
outlawed in the West.
Abraham Lincoln was a Kentucky-born
Southerner. But in 1860, he managed to
win the presidential election without
taking a single state in the South.
Within 2 months, 11 Southern states
broke away from the United States and
set out to create the Confederacy.
As tensions rose, they installed their
own president, Jefferson Davis, [music]
in their own White House in Montgomery,
Alabama.
And at 4:30 a.m. on the 12th of April,
1861, the first shots were fired by
Confederate troops at Fort Sumter.
The war escalated into a brutal
conflict.
At the Battle of Gettysburg alone,
51,000
men lost their lives in just 3 days.
The Confederate forces were fighting for
a new American nation.
>> So, this flag is what's called the first
national flag of the Confederacy. You
have the original 11 stars of the
Confederacy, and you have these uh red
and white stripes or bars on it.
>> It looks really quite like the Stars and
Stripes. Is that deliberate?
>> Well, that's part of the problem. When
you're on the battlefield, it's very
hard to tell the difference between it
and a United States flag, an American
flag.
>> can't tell who's who?
>> You can't tell who's who. That prompted
the Confederate government to create
another flag, a flag that would be used
in battles. And we just happen to have
an example of that here as well.
>> So, I can see that I've been thinking of
the Confederate flag wrongly. What I'm
actually thinking of is the Confederate
battle flag.
>> That's correct. It is the battle flag.
So, this is a purely military flag
designed to be used by troops in the
field. This particular flag was in the
Battle of Gettysburg.
You'll notice a lot of the battle damage
on it. One of the other things you might
notice is the number of stars.
>> So, that's 1 2 3
4 5 6 7 8 9
And one's gone missing at the end there,
but that's 13.
>> There's 13 stars.
>> That's wrong, isn't it?
>> By the time this flag was created in the
fall of 1861, the Confederate government
had admitted
two other slave-holding states
that never formally seceded from the
Union, Kentucky
and Missouri.
>> Isn't that clever that they were trying
to snap up any state that showed a
flicker of interest in the cause of the
Confederacy? This is a real case of
smoke and mirrors, isn't it? Even the
flag itself, there's more to it than you
think. It's not quite telling the
straightforward truth.
>> It feeds into this this sort of this
myth and how we understand the
Confederacy and the Civil War to this
day.
>> The bloody conflict dragged on year
after year. Many in the North began to
question whether it was all worth it.
Then, after 3 years of fighting, Lincoln
made a clever tactical move. He turned
the war into a crusade to abolish
slavery. In January 1863, Lincoln
drafted a statement, the Proclamation of
Emancipation.
It used the promise of liberation for
the enslaved people of the South to
strike a decisive blow against the
Confederacy.
>> This is a copy of the actual
Proclamation of Emancipation.
It says that on the first day of January
all persons held as slaves shall be then
thenceforth and forever free.
When it was read aloud in Washington
D.C. one witness reported that men
squealed, women fainted, and dogs
barked.
Thousands of copies of it were printed.
This one has rather beautiful
illustrations that tell the story.
Here's an angel releasing a poor little
boy from his chains.
Here are the bad old days an overseer
beating a slave and then here are the
freed and they are saying, "Give thanks
all ye people, give thanks to the Lord."
It rather looks in this image like
Lincoln himself is the Lord. The message
is clear to all the enslaved people here
in Georgia and across the South, "You
are now free."
But Lincoln was only promising the
abolition of slavery in rebel states.
Several slave-owning states on the
border of the Confederacy had remained
loyal to the Union. They were allowed to
keep their slaves. So was Lincoln
himself a real supporter of
emancipation?
There's a damning piece of evidence that
suggests that Lincoln's attitude towards
slavery was much more morally ambivalent
than you might assume.
He actually wrote to a newspaper in 1862
saying that his paramount objective was
to save the Union. It wasn't either to
save or destroy slavery.
He said that, "If I could save the Union
without freeing one single slave, then I
would."
Lincoln was the ultimate pragmatist. He
saw emancipation as just a tactic
towards achieving his bigger goal.
And he also saw another practical
benefit of ending slavery.
He could see that it would destroy the
economy of the South.
>> And it worked.
Enslaved African-Americans left the
plantations and fled to the north.
180,000
black soldiers came to serve in the
Union Army.
And in November 1864, the northern
general William Sherman set out to break
the spirit of the South.
With 60,000 Union troops, he made an
audacious attack behind Confederate
lines.
Flying the flag of emancipation, he
marched 300 miles from Atlanta to
Savannah, raiding farms, stealing
livestock, and destroying everything in
his path. In some places, the trail of
devastation was 60 miles wide.
>> Sherman made it very clear that he was
waging psychological warfare on the
people of Atlanta. He wrote them an open
letter that says, "You cannot qualify
war in harsher terms than I will. War is
cruelty. They who brought war into our
country deserve all the curses and
maledictions a people can pour on them."
Sherman said to another general, "I will
make Georgia howl."
Sherman's march is the stuff of legend.
The South remembers it as a brutal war
crime. To the north, it was a military
triumph celebrated in art and music.
>> Good morning.
>> Morning to you as well, Leslie.
>> Now, you are a musician. What was the
role of uh music in the in the Civil War
armies?
>> One of the chief reasons of musicians is
to inspire the soldiers.
>> Uh-huh.
>> So, if you have a patriotic song, or
even if you have a uh song that's well
known at home, that can put a spring in
your step. If you're marching, say 20 mi
in the swamps and marshes of Georgia,
that's mighty important.
>> Right. Let's sing a marching song. This
song I actually know, cuz we used to
sing this at the Girl Guides, or a
variation of it. We didn't have quite
these words. Um but this is this is a
Civil War version, isn't it?
>> Yes, indeed.
>> John Brown, let's give it a go. John
Brown was John the Baptist, of Christ we
are to see. Christ who of the
conscripted liberate
and soon throughout the sunny South the
slave shall all be free, for his soul is
marching on. Da da da da da da.
Glory, glory, hallelujah.
Glory, glory, hallelujah,
and his soul is marching on.
The song makes it sound really simple.
The slaves shall all be free. That's
what the troops in the north are here to
do, right?
>> Well, um according to some Union
soldiers, that's that's what they're
here to do, and perhaps that's even why
many of them joined in the first place.
>> As the war intensified, the Union tried
to justify the bloodshed and destruction
with the twin goals of abolishing
slavery and restoring national unity.
But as Sherman's march across the South
continued, the Union songs of liberation
took on a very hollow ring.
This is Ebenezer Creek. Waters are uh
silent, but they're very deep and murky,
and there are alligators hiding amongst
these trees.
On December the 8th, 1864,
14,000 Union soldiers under Brigadier
General Davis arrived at the creek
accompanied by thousands of former
slaves who were seeking protection from
Lincoln's army.
Confederate troops weren't far behind
them.
As night fell, pontoon bridges were
constructed across the water.
But Davis saw the new arrivals as a
hindrance. He called them "useless
Negroes". Trying to protect them, he
said, would be suicide.
He ordered that the African-American
men, women, and children be prevented
from crossing until the threat of more
Confederate troops ahead had been dealt
with.
Another commander, James Connolly, heard
what Davis was up to, and he thought
that it was wrong. He wrote this.
"I knew this must result in all these
Negroes being recaptured or perhaps
brutally shot. And I told his staff
officers what I thought of such an
inhuman, barbarous proceeding." [music]
But Davis didn't listen.
Davis's story turned out to be a lie.
There was no Confederate force in front.
And once his soldiers were across the
creek, he ordered the bridges to be
pulled up behind them.
600 men, women, and children were all
trapped on that side. The Confederate
troops were closing in on them. They
panicked. In the early hours of the
morning, they tried to cross these
swampy waters. Some of them put together
rafts.
Others used the trunks of trees.
Many of them drowned.
And those that didn't were either shot
by the Confederates
or sent back into slavery.
>> [music]
>> But Lincoln, the liberator, had another
surprise in store. On April the 11th,
1865, one of the windows of the White
House was opened.
President Abraham Lincoln, the hero of
the hour, leaned out of the window and
he made an impromptu speech to the
crowds gathered on the lawn. He was on
the verge of victory. He was looking
ahead to the future and he said that the
country really ought to think about
giving all these newly freed
African-Americans the vote. Of course,
this was completely against the values
and attitudes that the South had been
built upon.
In the crowd that day was a man with a
deep commitment to the Confederacy.
His name was John Wilkes Booth.
He was enraged by the president's
speech. He said, "By God, that's the
last speech he will ever make."
Three days later, Lincoln came here to
Ford's Theatre to see a show and Booth
made good on his promise. He got into
the theater and he shot the president at
close range in the head shouting, "Thus
to all tyrants."
Lincoln's bleeding body was carried out
of the theater and across the road and
to that house over there. He lingered on
for 24 hours and then he died, instantly
becoming a martyr to the cause of
emancipation and the Union.
Unionists descended into mourning.
Millions lined the streets as his
funeral train traveled 1,700 miles
across the country, finally reaching
[music] his burial place in Springfield,
Illinois.
>> Almost as soon as he was dead, images
like this one began to appear in the
press. In memory of Abraham Lincoln, the
reward of the just.
And he's been carried off up to heaven
by an angel. It's almost as if he's
become a religious figure. And like
Christ himself, he died at Easter. The
fatal shot was fired on Good Friday.
>> Soon after Lincoln's death, Charlotte
Scott, a former slave from Virginia,
gave $5 from her pay packet to begin
fundraising for a statue of Lincoln.
In April 1876, this photograph of
Charlotte was sold to visitors at the
grand unveiling of the Emancipation
Memorial in Washington.
The main speaker at the ceremony was
another former slave, now a politician
and reformer, Frederick Douglass. And he
began a reassessment of Lincoln's
memory.
>> Frederick Douglass was at the time
arguably the most important black man in
the country, and he didn't disappoint.
He very quickly launches into almost a
tirade about Lincoln's shortcomings. He
talks about the fact that Lincoln was
preeminently the white man's president.
That even though he had helped to free
enslaved people, Lincoln always did what
was in the best interest of his race.
But this man was president when we got
our freedom. And this is what he did to
help us get our freedom. So he's
balancing it.
>> Do you I people were surprised at the
time to hear words of criticism being
spoken at all.
>> Lincoln was an anti-slavery man, but he
was no abolitionist before the Civil
War.
He's someone who believed that slavery
was a legitimate institution, a
constitutionally protected institution,
[music] and because of that the federal
government could not touch that
institution where it already existed.
But he believed that if you contain it,
it would die a natural death. Might take
200 years, mind you, but it would
eventually die out.
>> Did Lincoln believe in racial equality?
>> Uh it depends upon what time in his life
we're talking about. In 1858,
he was engaged in a series of debates,
and Lincoln was in an environment where
he had to show the local people that he
was just as anti-black as they were.
>> To get their votes.
>> To get their votes, absolutely. And so
this is what he says to them.
I will say then that I am not, nor ever
have been, in favor of bringing about in
any way the social and political
equality of the white and black races.
And I, as much as any other man, is in
favor of having the superior position
assigned to the white race.
>> Woah.
>> And so in 1858, Lincoln is decidedly not
for racial equality. Not in this
statement, but not
in reality, either.
>> On the 9th of April, 1865,
the Confederate General Robert E. Lee
surrendered.
>> [music]
>> The war was over, but the shaping of its
place in history was just getting
started.
Lincoln's moral and political
shortcomings were largely forgotten.
The North celebrated the prospect of
unity restored. Rebels and traitors had
been crushed.
And slavery would now be abolished in
every state of the Union.
Whatever the truth really was, the
legend of Lincoln the Great Emancipator
who can sign slavery to the history
books was very powerful. Surely, this
promise of freedom to the enslaved would
now be delivered.
Wouldn't it?
It was a very limited kind of freedom.
Many states quickly instituted racial
segregation laws. Mixed marriages were
illegal in most Southern states. Black
people were banned from sharing the same
schools, restaurants, and transport as
whites. Separate but equal was the
phrase used to justify all these racist
laws which were introduced by a growing
number of states after the Civil War. It
was completely within their rights to do
this. The laws were just rubber-stamped
by the US Supreme Court.
So, millions of African Americans may
have been freed from slavery, but they
were still denied basic civil rights.
And it was when they were at work that
this fib of freedom was most cruelly
exposed.
Sharecropping was one example.
Former slaves had no money to buy land
or tools. So, they often had to borrow
from former slave owners to supply these
essentials and basic housing.
They were charged punitive interest on
the loans and forced to give up a large
share of the crop.
>> This is an account of an anonymous
victim of the system which was published
in 1904. He signed a contract with a
landlord. He got a cabin like this and
in return he was supposed to work to pay
back this debt. After 10 years though,
the debt had mysteriously got bigger,
not smaller.
He really wanted to leave and the
landowner said, "Well, you can as long
as you sign this paper saying that you
acknowledge that you are still in debt
to me."
This is what he says, "We would have
signed anything just to get away.
We stepped up, we did, and made our
marks.
That same night we were rounded up by a
constable and 10 or 12 white men who
aided him and we were locked up, every
one of us."
>> The next morning they were told the
papers they'd signed had bound them to
hard labor until all their debts were
paid.
>> He describes the next 3 years as hell on
earth.
The workers were kept in pens, rather
like animal pens. In the daytime they
had to go out to work to pay their debts
and at night they were locked up. The
conditions were appalling. He describes
the pens as the filthiest places in the
world. They were cesspools of nastiness.
>> And there was another betrayal to come.
The Emancipation Proclamation became law
as the 13th Amendment,
but it confirmed that the end of slavery
was a lie.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Slavery had been abolished, it said,
except as a punishment for crime. Which
meant that anyone who'd been convicted
of wrongdoing could be held in captivity
and made to work.
After the devastation of the war, the
South was rebuilding its cities and its
economy.
This is the site of the Chattahoochee
Brick Company in Atlanta.
In its heyday, it turned out 30 million
bricks a year.
After companies like this one had
spotted this loophole in the 13th
Amendment, they exploited it ruthlessly.
They went to the local prisons and hired
convicts and then worked them and worked
them to the bone.
Lincoln's emancipation had been
transformed into slavery of a new kind.
>> [music]
>> They called it convict leasing. And
between 1870 and 1920, 90% of the
prisoners sold into labor were African
Americans.
If you were found guilty of vagrancy,
fare avoidance, even talking to white
women, you could end up as a slave
again.
The city of Atlanta [music] was rebuilt
with the bricks prisoners made here.
Conditions were so bad that hundreds,
maybe thousands of them died.
Their bodies still buried
>> [music]
>> beneath the ruins.
In 1935,
a book called Black Reconstruction
[music] in America was published by the
historian W. E. B. Du Bois. After the
Civil War, he said, the slave went free,
stood for a brief moment in the sun,
and then moved back towards slavery.
>> [music]
>> In December 1934, convict leasing was
rebranded as Federal Prisons Industries
Incorporated.
The 13th Amendment is still in force to
this day.
Starbucks, Microsoft, and IBM have all
made use of prison laborers.
>> In 1867,
a Virginia journalist, Edward A.
Pollard, created a powerful Southern
alternative to the Northern version of
history. He called it The Lost Cause.
The title of the book inspired a revival
of Southern resistance against the
North.
Believers in The Lost Cause portrayed
the Old South as a vanished civilization
where plantation [music]
owners and happy slaves lived in
harmony.
Rebels and traitors were rebranded as
heroes and freedom fighters. And
Southern mothers, wives, and daughters
seized the opportunity to find pride in
the defeat of the fallen soldiers.
>> Women really become the face of The Lost
Cause in the late 19th and early 20th
century. Southern women formed this
organization called The United Daughters
of the Confederacy. They grew from 30
women at the original meeting of The
United Daughters
to 30,000 women in 10 years, to 100,000
women by World War I. They were
everywhere.
>> The United Daughters put up hundreds of
memorials to fallen Confederate heroes.
They also set out to ensure that the
next generation would learn the Southern
version of history.
They even appointed their own historian
general, Mildred Lewis Rutherford.
>> This is how she dressed when she would
give her presentations, her addresses.
>> And we're in the early 20th century
here, aren't we?
>> Correct. She's forever locked in 1860.
She was sort of a one-woman propaganda
machine. She made it her mission to
ensure that young children were going to
learn the true history of the South,
which is always a pro-Southern,
pro-Confederate history of the South.
>> What tools did she develop to do that,
then?
>> She created something called a measuring
rod for textbooks. You know, you use
this sort of a litmus test to say, "Does
this book have these things in it? If it
does, you need to reject it. You need to
deface it if it's in your school
library."
>> So, how how did she determine if the
book was right or not?
>> There are so many reasons to get rid of
a book, it's hard to imagine there were
any books left. For example, reject a
book that calls the Confederate soldier
a traitor or rebel and the war a
rebellion. Reject a book that speaks of
the slaveholder of the South as cruel
and unjust to his slaves.
And reject a textbook that glorifies
Abraham Lincoln and vilifies Jefferson
Davis.
>> It's so unsubtle.
>> It's very unsubtle and she's not a
subtle woman at all.
>> This is very clever historical
propaganda machine they've got working
here, then, isn't it?
>> Yes, they don't miss a beat. They cover
all the bases.
>> [music]
>> Mildred Rutherford also taught a version
of history that said that the
Confederacy's noble cause was to stand
up for individual states' rights against
the tyrannical and interfering big
government from the north.
>> Southerners considered themselves the
inheritors of the revolutionary
generation, that they were being
patriotic because they were abiding by
the 10th Amendment to the Constitution,
which defended states' rights. That they
needed to be able to make their own
decisions about their state. The thing
that's always left out of that, even to
this day, while the South fought the war
for states' rights,
they never say the states' rights to
maintain slavery.
>> That's what they mean though, isn't it?
>> They wouldn't say so, but that's exactly
what it boils down to.
>> The lost cause buried this inconvenient
truth. But in the 1860s, they were a bit
more honest about it.
>> [music]
>> Motivation of a secessionist, uh it's
pretty simple. All we need to do is look
at their words and what they said. They
all to a state said, "This is about
defending the institution of slavery."
Mississippi said it right up front.
Mississippi's ordinance of secession,
the very first sentence, they said, "Our
cause is inextricably linked to the
institution of slavery, the greatest
material interest in the world."
>> In 1915, [music]
50 years after Lincoln's victory, a new
movie was about to reawaken the
lingering prejudice and hatred of the
Civil War.
>> The title of the film made it sound like
a rousing patriotic story. It was called
The Birth of a Nation.
Its director, D. W. Griffith, was the
son of a Confederate veteran, and he was
determined to make the first [music]
great Civil War movie.
But the film's name masked the nasty
source material that it was based upon,
which was a novel called The Clansman, a
historical romance of the Ku Klux Klan.
The Ku Klux Klan was a white supremacist
movement that emerged [music] in the
19th century.
Set during the Civil War and its
aftermath, The Birth of a Nation
portrays the Klan as the white knights
of the South.
It showed African-Americans, often
played by white actors in blackface, as
violent criminals eager to molest white
women.
In this scene, the Klan takes its
revenge.
The Birth of a Nation smashed all box
office records, taking today's
equivalent of nearly $2 billion.
A week before the premiere in Atlanta, a
former preacher, William Simmons, got
together 15 of his [music] friends at a
local landmark, Stone Mountain. They
climbed to the summit, lashed together
two [music] planks of wood, and set them
alight
for the whole of Georgia to see. Simmons
was relaunching the Ku Klux Klan.
This was a very interesting use of
history. The Klan had existed in the
19th century. It was a thing, but it had
sort of fizzled out. When Simmons
revived it, he was reopening a chapter
of history that had been consigned to
the past.
The film and the novel would help
Simmons bring the Klan back to life.
On the night of the premiere, Simmons
and the other clansmen decided to hold a
recruitment drive. So, they came in
procession along this street. It's
Peachtree Street. It's the main street
of Atlanta. They were riding horses, and
they were firing rifles into the air to
salute the new film. And all over the
country, he organized for other clansmen
to dress up in their clan robes and
hoods and to parade outside cinemas.
And in a local newspaper, Simmons placed
a recruitment advert. He drawn it
himself. It was printed alongside
adverts for the film.
Within 10 years, it's been estimated
that 4 million people had joined [music]
the clan.
But the revival was based on fibs.
The historic clan never burnt crosses.
That idea was invented by the novel. And
the original clan costumes weren't all
white.
The ones we know today were created for
the film. As the director put it, solely
from the viewpoint of theatrical
effectiveness.
Between them, they were reinventing the
terrifying iconography of the Ku Klux
Klan. They were playing with history to
suit their purposes. By making the clan
sound old, they also made it sound
somehow authentic. They were trying to
give it a veneer of respectability
to cover up their murderous intentions.
The revival of the clan unleashed a new
reign of terror. The trademark hoods and
crosses would now accompany lynchings
across America.
Thousands [music] of black Americans
were kidnapped, tortured, and murdered.
>> Nearly 25 years after the birth of a
nation, the American Civil War went to
the movies again in 1939.
Based on the novel by Margaret Mitchell,
Gone with the Wind would put the unity
back into the United States. It's one of
the most successful films ever made.
The film had everything a girl could
want. Elegant Southern Belles, ravishing
landscapes, [music]
a swooping score, and devastating
Southern gentleman.
The film opens on the eve of Civil War.
It tells the story of Scarlett O'Hara,
the wealthy daughter of a cotton
plantation owner in Georgia, and follows
her struggle to survive the devastation
of war.
>> We will now put on your hoop skirt.
>> Let's get it over your head.
>> Fantastic.
And where's my way in?
Bit of a Barbie theme going on here.
Am I going to fit in?
>> Yes, you will. If not, we'll just have
to suck your corset in some more.
>> I'm guessing Scarlett O'Hara's waist as
we speak.
>> Just so you know, getting out of it's a
lot easier than getting into it.
And for the final touch,
you will look like a princess.
There you go.
You are darling, darling.
>> Scarlett is the flawed but irresistible
mistress of an estate called Tara, and
this house is said to have inspired it.
Today, it's a museum celebrating the
spirit of Gone with the Wind.
Can you tell me what's your relationship
with Gone with the Wind?
>> Well, it just happens to be my most
favorite movie in the whole wide world.
>> favorite movie in the whole wide world?
>> And that I've watched probably 30, 40
times. I enjoy the clothing from the
movie. I enjoy the time period. I enjoy
the romance of that period and the
genteelness of that period.
>> By the 1930s, when Gone with the Wind is
a huge sensation, isn't it? It's a
massive commercial success. There must
have been people in the north who were
as much in love with it as people from
the south. Is that right?
>> Absolutely. America went crazy.
>> The whole of America.
>> of America went crazy over Gone with the
Wind.
>> Is there a sense that 60 years
previously they had been totally at
loggerheads, things had been terrible,
but by the time we get to Gone with the
Wind, there's something of a process of
coming together, healing, reconciliation
had taken place and everyone could enjoy
the story, do you
>> Yes. Yes. You're exactly right.
>> The spirited character of Scarlett
helped the film to transcend the
divisions of the Civil War.
Her triumph over adversity now speak to
a generation who'd gone without during
the Great Depression of the 1930s.
But to achieve that process of healing
and reconciliation between north and
[music] south, the old fibs and
distortions were dusted down once again.
Gone with the Wind was an elegant
[music] airbrushing of history.
It's a lament for a courtly, noble way
of life that no longer exists. In fact,
it's the lost cause again, but dressed
up in better costumes.
In the book that inspired the film, some
of the sinister politics of the old
south are clear to see.
Scarlett learns that her husband, and
all the men in the story, are members of
the Ku Klux Klan.
And both book and film pedal one
enduring and dangerous southern Civil
War fib.
Mammy is a kind-hearted matriarchal
figure, just like one of the family.
But the fact remains that Mammy was
enslaved.
There's no escaping it. Gone with the
Wind is a romanticized version of a dark
period of history.
I'm always one for dressing up, but when
you bear that in mind,
>> [snorts]
>> I don't feel entirely comfortable
dressed like this.
The film may have tried to prettify the
past, but with the character of Mammy,
there was no escaping the bare-faced
racism of the present.
The role was played by Hattie McDaniel.
She was herself the daughter of enslaved
African-Americans, and she was
recognized for the part with an Oscar,
the first black actor to get one. But
when it came to the film's fancy
premiere, just down the road in Atlanta,
there were segregation laws in place
that prevented black and white people
from sitting down together. So, Hattie
wasn't invited. The producers thought
about it, decided it would be awkward,
and asked her to stay away.
A children's choir, dressed as
plantation workers, had been booked to
perform that evening.
And one of the choir
was a 10-year-old called Martin Luther
King.
24 years later, a growing civil rights
movement was campaigning for change. In
1963, a massive march on Washington was
planned.
>> [music]
>> By this time, the choir boy had grown
up. He was now a Baptist minister and
activist, and the march was going to be
addressed by Dr. Martin Luther King.
Right here, black voices were creating a
new version of history.
>> [singing]
>> August the 28th, 1963,
100 years after Lincoln's Emancipation
Proclamation,
>> [cheering]
>> more than 200,000 people gathered at the
Lincoln Memorial to challenge the legacy
of the Civil War.
>> [cheering]
>> The nation was celebrating 100 years
since the Emancipation Proclamation, and
civil rights organizations knew this was
a time to think about how far we hadn't
come as a nation. There's something
really powerful about a mass of people
facing Abraham Lincoln, who's considered
one of the greatest presidents outside
of the founding era,
to challenge the idea of inequality
among the citizenry. And what does it
mean to have masses of people looking at
this symbol and asking for the nation to
finally deliver on its promises?
>> The phrase that people remember from
this speech is, "I have a dream." But
there's another phrase that particularly
interests you, isn't there?
>> Yes, it's the idea of the promissory
note.
When King opens his speech, he talks
about the fact that African-Americans
have essentially been written a bad
check. And that the check was first
written by Lincoln and his promises of
emancipation. And the country was unable
to fulfill the promise of that note.
King is really making critical the point
of the March. That it's not just about a
declaration of freedom. But that there
are economic responsibilities, economic
goals that the March also was advocating
for. Jobs, better schools, the right to
vote. King is really showing us his most
revolutionary and his most expansive
vision of what civil rights actually
meant.
>> The story had been that Lincoln had
healed the wounds of the battle between
the north and the south. But King was
saying, "No, there's more to this story
than that. What's not being healed are
the wounds left by slavery."
He was using history. He was using all
this to put civil rights onto the
agenda.
>> I think this March will go down as
one of the greatest, if not the
greatest, demonstrations for freedom and
human dignity
ever held in the United States.
>> It was powerful. The Civil Rights Act of
1964 ended racial discrimination at work
and prohibited segregation in public
spaces.
The divisive legacy of slavery and the
Civil War was finally beginning to be
confronted.
>> [cheering]
>> Another of the resonant phrases from
King's epic speech was, "Let freedom
ring from the Stone Mountain of
Georgia."
By that, he was trying to bury the
memory of the clan.
But in fact, the echoes of the lost
cause would continue to resonate
throughout the country.
>> [music]
>> In 1972,
a huge Civil War Memorial was completed
on the side of Stone Mountain.
Three Confederate leaders were carved
into the rock: Jefferson Davis, Robert
E. Lee, and Stonewall Jackson. As
recently as August 2017,
a member of the Ku Klux Klan sought
permission to burn another cross at
Stone Mountain.
The application was turned down.
>> 150 years after the end of the Civil
War,
there are hundreds of Confederate
memorials across the South.
One of them is the centerpiece of a
little park in Charlottesville,
Virginia.
But some don't want to celebrate what
this statue stands for.
>> Mario, what's the story of your
relationship to this park?
>> Uh this is the park where my wife and I
got married roughly 8 years ago.
>> And what did your father say to you at
the wedding?
>> Uh
my dad uh
he told
the photographer he didn't want
that picture that uh statue in our in
our wedding pictures.
>> Can you remember what he said about the
statue?
>> You know, it represented the oppression
of the African-American people by
individuals like Robert E. Lee uh
Stonewall Jackson, etc.
>> And your father, he's from Georgia, is
he?
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> And so that statue to him it had real
horrible meaning.
>> It does.
It does.
>> I'm sorry that the American Civil War
turned up to your wedding.
>> Yeah.
Unreal.
>> Under mounting pressure, in February
2017, the city council of
Charlottesville voted to change the name
of Lee Park.
Then they said [music] they wanted to
remove Lee's statue.
Many were against this.
Jack, what's the case for keeping the
statue of General Lee just as it is?
>> Well, it's a magnificent piece of art.
It represents our culture and our
history, and it's a good talking point
for talking about all the all the things
that happened during the Civil War and
after the Civil War.
If you can imagine the park without it,
what's left to talk about?
One of the complaints about the statue
is that celebrates just one side, and
the other side needs to get its own
chance to speak. I would agree
completely with putting more signs
around it or or using other educational
materials to tell both sides of the
story. The problem is that those who
want to remove the monument don't want
to tell both sides of the story. They
want to, as they put it, change the
narrative, so it's just one side of the
story. They have a view of the matter
that
the Confederates and Lee were just evil
people, and we shouldn't have any
statues of them. I'm afraid I disagree
with that.
>> There was a kind of modern-day Civil War
standoff.
The name that was chosen for the park
was Emancipation Park. But standing
right in the middle of it was the statue
of General Lee. It was like he was still
in the heat of battle. This is a really
strange moment when two different
versions of history were colliding.
There is the Unionist story,
Emancipation Park, and the Confederate
story, General Lee.
And then things turned ugly.
On the 11th of August, 2017,
an organization called Unite the Right
gathered [music] in Charlottesville for
a rally. Hundreds of white supremacists
marched to protest against the removal
of General Lee's statue in Emancipation
Park. On the other side, civil rights
protesters mobilized.
There were Confederate flags everywhere,
and people were shouting, "Blood and
soil." And, "You will not replace us."
The past was at the heart of this very
21st century conflict. The organizer of
the Unite the Right rally said that they
were doing it to stand up for our
history.
But the history the statue represented
has hidden layers.
>> Well, the statue is very interesting in
that, though Lee was a Confederate
general, lived in the 19th century, it
wasn't commissioned until 1917 and
actually erected in 1924.
And it was erected during a time
of heightened racial violence against
African-Americans, particularly
lynching.
>> And it's part of that moment in history
as well as the Civil War.
>> Yes, it is. And make no mistake that
these monuments, these figures, were
meant to in some way, both directly and
indirectly, instill fear.
>> The confrontation continued into the
12th of August.
>> This is the Blind Boys of Alabama. Look
at them.
>> That day, one of the supporters of Unite
the Right drove his car into a crowd of
counter-protesters.
33 people were injured, and a civil
rights activist, Heather Heyer, was
killed.
>> [music]
>> Not too far from where we are, perhaps a
30-second walk, um the violent clashes
claimed the life of one of the
counter-protesters, Heather Heyer. Um
and it still uh shakes the city of
Charlottesville, the University of
Virginia community to its core.
>> It seems to me that the woman who was
killed, Heather Heyer, the
counter-protester, in a way she was a
victim of the Civil War. Is that fair?
>> I think so. Um and perhaps a victim of a
new Civil War, one that
um is re-emerging, and one that did not
really conclude in the middle of the
19th century. We are still in many ways
fighting similar battles about what it
means to be American, about what it
means to be white or perhaps black
Americans, and
and what it means to have this shared
history in a really complex way.
>> In the 1850s, it was north versus south.
Black America didn't have a voice. Now
it does. And the new fault lines are
just as dangerous and violent.
History is never fixed. It's a cultural
and political battleground.
And national mythologies are usually a
combination of conflicting versions,
full of distortions, legends, myths, and
lies.
Abraham [music] Lincoln set up a story
about the Civil War that promised a
happy ending of unity, freedom, and
equality.
That's the message of the Lincoln
Memorial. It's set in stone.
But perhaps that message of permanence
is the biggest fib of all.
Next time,
post-war supremacy,
>> You have lift off.
>> Lift off has happened. It's gone.
>> and the fibs lurking beneath the surface
of the American dream, witch hunts,
>> Have you ever been a member of the
Communist Party?
>> What's that? What's that? What's that?
>> UFOs,
and atomic tourism.
>> [music]